# Andrea Cristina Bravo Balado

Address: 1068CE, Amsterdam E-mail: <a href="mailto:andreacbravob@gmail.com">andreacbravob@gmail.com</a>

Website: <u>andreabravo.me</u>
Nationalities: Venezuelan and Spanish

Phone: +31644089932 Birth date: 03/11/1986

I am a junior software engineer, with a master's degree in Artificial Intelligence from Vrije Universiteit Amsterdam. Before moving to the Netherlands, I worked for two years as a software engineer in a Venezuelan banking institution. Communication is one of my strongest qualities and I believe in responsibility and in solving problems creatively, paying close attention to each and every detail. I am looking forward to continuing my professional career in a role where I can combine linked data, machine learning and/or information retrieval with software development, in a dynamic and learning environment.

### Education

### Vrije Universiteit Amsterdam | Amsterdam, Netherlands

2010-2014

# MS in Artificial Intelligence, Knowledge Technology and Intelligent Internet Applications specialization.

The full thesis can be found here.

#### **Abstract**

Linking historical datasets and making them available for the Web has increasingly become a subject of research in the field of digital humanities. In this master project, we focused on discovering links between ships from a dataset of Dutch maritime events and newspaper articles from historical archives. We have taken a two-stage approach: first, an heuristic-based method for record linkage and then machine- learning algorithms for article classification to be used for filtering in combination with domain features. Evaluation of the linking method has shown that certain domain features were indicative of mentions of ships in newspapers. Moreover, the classifier methods scored near perfect precision in predicting ship related articles.

#### Universidad Rafael Belloso Chacín | Maracaibo, Venezuela

2004-2008

#### BS in Software Engineering.

Graduated with Cum Laude honors.

Extra curricular activities: Centro de Transferencia de Tecnología (Technology Transfer Center) and IglURBE: University's linux user group.

## Experience

#### **Volunteer English teacher | Casa Migrante Amsterdam**

April 2014 – Present | Amsterdam, Netherlands

- Teacher for Spanish-speaking adults in the Netherlands.
- Planning course content and lessons.

#### **Editor | Amsterdamdo**

March 2011 – Present | Amsterdam, Netherlands

- Travel blog about Amsterdam.
- Targeted to Spanish-speaking travelers.
- Personalized travel itineraries for visits in Amsterdam.

Andrea Cristina Bravo Balado 1/2

#### Software and support engineer | Desarrollo Fintec de Costa Rica

May 2008 - February 2010 | San José, Costa Rica and Maracaibo, Venezuela

- Support and development of an inter-banking application that manages incoming and outgoing direct debits and credits between the bank and the Central Bank of Venezuela.
- Worked with Banco Occidental de Descuento (BOD) and Banfoandes (now Banco Bicentenario) in Venezuela and shortly with Scotiabank in Costa Rica.
- Developed with Java EE, Spring and Hibernate using Eclipse. Deployed on Apache Tomcat.
- Worked with MS SQL Server at one banking institution and PostgreSQL in another.
- Support in real time when needed.

#### Internship as a software developer | Qualitex Servicios Tecnológicos

January 2008 – March 2008 | Maracaibo, Venezuela

- Adjusting an in-house help desk/support ticket application to a different domain for Radio Marina de Venezuela.
- Existing software was designed for hardware and software technical support and needed to work for a company that provides support for communication and navigation equipment for the maritime activity.
- Assessing requirements directly with the contact person at Radio Marina de Venezuela.
- Worked with C# and MS SQL.

# Cisco's Fundamentals of Java Programming teaching assistant | Universidad Rafael Belloso Chacín (URBE)

January 2007 - March 2008 | Maracaibo, Venezuela

- Teaching assistant of Cisco's Fundamentals of Java Programming course.
- Helping students with weekly assignments and case studies.
- Standing in for the instructor when needed.
- Organization and management of enrollments, workshops and conferences for the Technology Transfer Center.

#### **Swimming instructor | Artes Swim Academy**

August 2002 - August 2004 | Maracaibo, Venezuela

- Full-time work during the summer time as swimming instructor for children from 2.5 to 5 years old.
- Providing special attention to children with Down syndrome.
- Assisting in other summer camp activities with young children.

## Languages

**Español:** Native or bilingual proficiency. **English:** Native or bilingual proficiency. **Nederlands:** Elementary proficiency.

#### Hobbies

I enjoy cooking, baking and creating my own healthy and minimal recipes and posting them on my blog. I find writing very relaxing. Swimming is my favorite sport and I was part of a swimming team when I was younger. I also like flamenco dancing and singing. I'm very curious so I love to read about history and how things work.

Andrea Cristina Bravo Balado 2/2